- 现在是什么时刻？
What time is it?
- 比赛时刻！呼！
Game time! Whoo!
来自北卡罗来纳州...
From North Carolina...
身高六尺六的后卫，麦可·乔丹！
at guard, six-six,Michael Jordan!
即使我已经站在世界的巅峰，
day after day that I stepped on the basketball court,
但每天当我踏入球场时，
even though I was on top of the world,
我觉得我仍有些东西要去证明。
I felt like I had something to prove.
在乔丹的最后一赛季，
After Michael Jordan's final season,
NBA联盟再次颁给他一座最有价值球员的奖项，
the NBA gave him yet another Most Valuable Player Award,
据说理由非常简单：
and said the reason is simple：
“在13个赛季后，你仍能每晚站出来，
"After 13 seasons,you still go out every night.
而且打得像麦可·乔丹。”
and play like Michael Jordan."
当乔丹准备出场时，
When Jordan would go out for the spotlight introduction,
他会抬头看看座位席上，
he would look up into the stands and he would realize.
发现那晚起码有人，
that there was at least someone up there that night.
那些素未谋面的，或者不会再见的球迷在那里，
who had never seen him before,who would never see him again.
而此刻是他们拥有乔丹的一个时刻！
And this would be the one Michael Jordan moment...they ever had.
而他会说我是为那些人而战。
And he would say he was playing for those people there
我们有次连续六场作战客场，
We had a six-game road trip.Michael had some spasms
麦可腰部有些痉挛，
in his lower back.
所以我们不得不逐步地，你知道...
And we literally had to, you know...
搀扶他下了巴士，再下飞机，
carry him off the bus, off the plane to the bus...
再坐巴士去酒店。
from the bus to the hotel.
你知道吗，吓了我一跳...
You know, it amazed me...
他那晚比赛还砍下了40分。
He went out and got 40 points that night.
他就是这种球员。他想要大家看到他的精彩球技，
This is the kind of player he was. He wanted everybody
to see his special skill，
他不想让那些喜爱篮球的观众没有这种机会。
And he didn't want people who loved basketball...not to have that opportunity.
当季后赛开始，
When the playoffs began,
麦可心里已经知道，
in his heart Michael already knew.
那可能会是他最后的几场比赛，
that these would be his last games，
但这不会是怀旧的告别演出赛，
But this would be no nostalgic farewell tour，
他决心以自己
He was determined to go out on his own terms
...冠军的姿色站出来。
...as a champion.
公牛队第一轮的对手是年轻，充满朝气的
the Bulls' first-round opponents were the New Jersey Nets
新泽西网队。
young and full of hope.
麦可统治了比赛！
Michael was dominant!
公牛三场横扫对手，
It was a three-game sweep,
建立了坚韧的心志，对等于身体的才能。
built on mental toughness as much as physical talent.
而对于麦可,心灵的成长旅程
And for Michael, the way to develop the mind
则总是刻骨铭心的！
had always been through the heart!
许多家长问我，
A lot of parents ask me,
“呃，你能给我的孩子一些建议吗？”
"Well, what advice would you give my kids?"
而我的建议就是:“让他们享受球赛。”
And my advice would be let them just enjoy the game.
我认为他们年轻的时候该学的
I think what they have to learn more about at that young age...is
是对球赛的热爱
their love for the game.
一旦他们培养了那种兴趣，心理关就容易多了。
And once they've developed that, then the mental part is easy.
我直到高中时才认识到这一点。
I didn't really get instruction until I was a junior in high school.
最初时，我只是喜欢球赛，自由发展我的技术。
First, I just loved the game and I let my skills develop.
所以我相信迟点再学
So I believe in learning late.
先玩然后再学。
playing early, but learning late.
麦可对球赛的热爱
Michael's love of the game was born...
是整个下午都耗在北卡罗来纳州，他老家威明顿
in his hometown of Wilmington, North Carolina...
的球场上产生的。
during long afternoons on the play grounds.
在后院里，在他们"史诗般"一对一的战斗中，
His older brother, Larry, helped Michael hone his game...
他的哥哥，赖瑞，帮助麦可磨练他的球技。
n their epic battles of one-on-one at their backyard hoop.
而麦可第一次深刻的经验教训
But Michael's first hard lesson
是在他尝试成为兰尼高中的校队时。
would come when he tried out for the varsity team at Laney High.
当我还是个高中二年级学生时，
When I was a sophomore in high school.
像大多数高中生一样，
like most high school kids.
你把所有的精力，所有的动力，和激情
you get all the energy and all the motivation and excitement...
都注入成为校队的事情上，那是件大事。
of making your varsity team, which is a big thing.
名气在学校很重要。
Status is a lot when you're in high school.
所以你可以想像我有多失望。
So you can imagine the disappointment that I got...
当我觉得我应该能进入校队，
I felt like I should have made the team,
却没能进入校队。
but then didn't make the team.
我哭了，情绪完全失控。
I'm crying, I lost my emotions totally.
而我母亲则过来对我说，
My mother came to me and said,
“用那精力向你的教练，同龄人和同学证明，
"Use that energy to prove to the coach and to your peers and your classmates，
他们犯了个错误。”
that they made a mistake."
你付出你最好的表现，
You give it your best.
你这么努力地去得分，
You try so hard and you get to the point.
我知道我做的到。
I know I can do it.
而如果你再试一次，你就有可能成功，
And if you try one more time, you are able to achieve it.
那就更进一步。
It's going one step farther.
那就是不放弃，
That's not giving up,
那就是尽你最大的努力。
it's giving your best.
当我知道我不能作贡献时，我会选择走开。
I only will walk away when I know I do not have anything else to give.
失望是那么的深，像一个伤口，
The disappointment was so deep, like a cut,
它也让我重燃斗志，
it struck the fire in me.
使我不会再次忍受那种痛苦。
to make sure that I never endure that type of pain again.
在季后赛的第二轮，
In the second-round of the playoffs.
麦可带着复仇之心回到家乡。
Michael returned home with a vengeance.
迎战夏洛特黄蜂队，
Playing the Charlotte Hornets,
这可能会是麦可最后一次在北卡罗来纳州职业出赛了。
it would be Michael's last professional appearance in North Carolina.
回到家乡总是感觉很好...当你在这长大，
It's always been a treat to come back home...when you've grown up here
然后去到外面依靠自己的能力成为一位人物，再回来
and you go out and become a man on your own，And then come back home
展示已经不同的你。
to show what's evolved of that person.
对于那些从他是北卡学生就看着乔丹的球迷来说，
For fans who had watched him since his days as a Carolina schoolboy,
现在呈现的不仅是他的技巧还有他的意志力。
what emerged now was not just the skill but the will power.
那些记得乔丹的潜能的球迷，
Those who remembered his raw potential.
现在看到了一生努力的成果。
now saw the results of a lifetime of hard work.
他先进二队并努力练习，
He would go to JV practice and practice,
之后他就去正队练习了(即他成为了正选)。
and then he'd go to varsity practice.
我们打比赛，比赛结束后，
We'd play ball games, and after the games were over,
他则做我们称为所谓的"自杀"或跑底线...
he'd run what we called "suicides"or line drills...
就他一个人在那里跑。
he'd run those by himself.
那时我就惊叹他那种，
I just marveled at his work habits even then.
将所有都注入竞争的习性，
With his competitiveness to go with all that dedication,
你知道，值得一看。
you know, it was something to see.
麦可在进攻端最弱的是他的跳投。
The weakest part of Michael's game on the offensive end was his shooting.
而他显然知道些...
So he obviously mastered something...
每个人都说他大学出来后也做不好。
that everybody said he couldn't do when he came out of college.
于是他不断地跳投，跳投，跳投，连续地跳投。
And he did it by shooting and shooting and shooting and shooting consistently.
另外人们说他不是个很好的防守球员，
The other thing that people told him that he wasn't a really good defensive player.
而他找到了方法
And he found a way
不仅变成了一位伟大的防守球员
not only to become a great defensive player
还成为了NBA最佳防守球员。
but the best defensive player in the NBA.
这个家伙说，“那些是我的弱点，
This guy said, "Those are my weaknesses,
我要把它们变为我的强项”而且他做到了！
I'm going to figure out how to make those my strengths." And he did it!
当第一次我带他时，
I got a glimpse, really, of Michael Jordan...
我瞄了麦可.乔丹一眼，真的。
and what he was all about the first time ever coached him.
差不多还有两分钟，我叫了个暂停，
About two minutes to go in the game, I called a time-out.
我们落后两分... 比赛僵持不下。
And we were down two... it was right there in the balance.
我在嚼口香糖,嘴边沾了些残渣。
And I had some little powder on my mouth
我嚼得太大力了，
from where I chewed some gum and chewed it so hard
以致嘴角真的起了泡泡。
that it really had become powder.
而麦可拿了杯水递给我，
And Michael grabbed a cup of water and he handed it to me,
他说，“喝点水，
and he said, "Take a drink of this water.
把你嘴角的东西清理掉。
Clear that stuff off your mouth.
我不会让你输掉你的第一场比赛的。”
I'm not going to let you lose your first game."
人生中有关任何事情的信念
The level of faith that I have in anything in life
是授自于你的父母。
is taught to you from your parents.
它是一种我不会用任何事物交换的特性！
It is a trait that I would never trade anything for!
如果我能传递些什么给我孩子的话...
And if I can ever pass anything on to my kids...
那会是对生活中任何事物的乐观态度。
it would be to be optimistic about everything in life.
他那时只个是北卡罗来纳州大学的新生，
He was only a freshman at the University of North Carolina,
但是在1982年NCAA冠军赛的危急关头时，
but with the 1982 NCAA Championship at stake,
球队的命运系于乔丹之手,而他却从未迟疑过。
his team's fate was in his hands, and he never hesitated.
回传给乔丹,左侧中距离跳投！
Goes back to Michael Jordan, jumper from out on the left!
北卡即将赢得NCAA冠军！
The Tar Heels are going to win the national championship!
在我投中那一球之后，我父亲过来对我说，
After I hit the shot, my father came to me and said.
这是伟大旅程的开始。
this was the start of something big.
他不知那是什么，我也不知那是什么，
He didn't know what it was. I didn't know what it was.
不过我真的相信他。
But I did believe him.
早上好，女士们先生们，
Good morning, ladies and gentlemen.
欢迎来到23号航班。
Welcome to flight 23.
请确认系好安全带...
Please make sure your seat belts are securely fastened...
并熄灭所有冒烟之物。
and extinguish all smoking materials.
麦可来时，
Michael came along at a time...
正值世界全球化，
when globalization really was occurring.
也正是媒体爆炸的时代，
and an explosion in media was occurring.
而他正好助长了那爆炸。
And he helped drive that explosion.
嘿，麦可，是什么让你成为世界上最好的球员呢？
Yo, Mike, what makes you the best player in the universe?
是你的发型？
Is it the haircut?
不是，玛斯。
No, Mars.
是这双鞋？
Is it the shoes?
有很多事物因他而大受欢迎。
There have been so many things that he has popularized.
这短裤，这双鞋，“一定是这双鞋。”
The shorts, the shoes, "Must be the shoes."
一定是这双鞋！鞋！鞋！
Money, it's got to be the shoes! Shoes! Shoes!
我觉得麦可已经超越了所有
I think Michael has transcended every boundary
性别、种族、年龄，和运动的界限。
of gender and race and age and sport.
我想他已成为我们日常文化的一部份了。
I think he's become  of apart of our everyday culture.
在职业生涯中我错失了9000多球...
I've missed more than 9,000 shots in my career...
在我看来他之所以能成为一位如此独特的商业标志，
I think what made him so special as a marketing icon
是因为那是他本性天生的。
is that he was natural.
今天，当人们真的尝试模仿麦可，
Today, when everyone really tries to be like Mike,
或努力地去刻造一个传奇人物
they're trying so hard to invent a persona,
我想人们可以看得出来，
I think that people see through that.
那是经不起时间的考验，站不住脚的。
and it doesn't stand the test of time.
在我人生中我不断失败，失败，不停地失败，
I've failed over and over and over again in my life,
那就是我成功的原因。
and that is why I succeed.
大家下午好，再次欢迎 。
Good afternoon, everyone, and welcome once again.
来到公牛队季后赛...
the Bulls basketball. playoff basketball...
我们把目光转移到东区决赛...
as we move to the Eastern Conference Finals...
公牛队和印第安那溜马队。
the Bulls and the Indiana Pacers.
在常规赛两队各胜两场，
These two teams were two and two in the regular season.
但是真正的对抗开始于星期天下午的芝加哥。
But the rivalry really begins on a Sunday afternoon in Chicago.
米勒和乔丹，都是骨子里
Miller and Jordan and a cast of characters
非赢不可的角色。
that is not afraid to win.
麦可，滑了一下，摔倒了，起来切入禁区，
Here's Michael, slips and falls down, gets back up into the lane,
跳出包夹，后仰，出手，精彩！
hops through, falls, fires on the rim and it's good!
而印第安那溜马队
The Indiana Pacers
带着外线投篮和强硬的打法，
with their outside shooting and the physical play.
全队一心地抵抗麦可和公牛队。
were a team custom-built to defeat Michael and the Bulls.
系列赛的前两场，
In the first two games of the series.
即使公牛队都赢了，
even though the Bulls would win both games.
但是很显然溜马队，
it was clear that the Pacers
会亮出他们第一波的真正的考验。
would pose their first real test.
罗斯收回来，现在，罗斯，球被麦可拍掉，
Rose backs in. Now, Rose, stripped by Michael.
传给哈柏。
To Harper.
哈柏带球快攻，
Harper on the run.
传给汤尼， 库科奇又传给麦可。
Lead pass, Toni, Kukoc to Michael.
乔丹大力扣篮！
He dunks the ball!
哦，天哪！
Oh, my!
接下来的两场比赛，场地移师到印第安那，
For the next two games, the scene shifted to Indiana.
在他们的主场，溜马依靠他们不知疲倦的后卫，
On their home court, the Pacers would win game three
瑞基.米勒，赢得了第三比赛。
behind their tireless guard, Reggie Miller.
球前传给了马克·杰克逊，
Lead pass ahead for Mark Jackson.
这就是溜马想要的。
This is what Indiana wants.
他们把球传给米勒投三分...球进！
They run to Miller for three...got it!
第四场，在最后的几秒钟公牛还领先1分，
In game four, the Bulls led  by a point in the final seconds,
米勒和乔丹又较起劲儿来了。
when Miller and Jordan would square off again.
开始了，迈基在拿球找人。
Here we go.McKey holding, looking.
米勒来到弧顶。
Here comes Miller to the top.
米勒，接球，米勒，看了一下...
Miller, a catch. Miller, a look...
他投进了！
he hit it!
瑞基·米勒，将它投进了！
Reggie Miller.knocked it down.
还剩0.4秒。
Four-tenths of a second left.
瑞基！瑞基！瑞基！
Reggie, Reggie, Reggie!
汤尼，发球时间快到了。
Toni, out near the time line.
在看，在看，在看，在看，在看，在看。
Looking, looking, looking, looking, looking, looking.
把球给了麦可，
Got it to Michael.
球进了又弹了出来！
And it went in and out!
球打到篮板后又刷框而出，溜马赢得了比赛。
Hit the board and spun out, and Indiana wins the game.
随着系列赛2比2打平，
With the series tied at two.
而疲惫也在损耗公牛队。
fatigue was taking its toll on the Bulls.
而同时，在西区，
And meanwhile, out West,
由未来名人堂的球员卡尔.马龙与约翰.斯托克顿领军，
the Utah Jazz were rolling towards the finals.
犹他爵士队正向总决赛迈进。
Led by future Hall of Famers Karl Malone and John Stockton,
爵士们统治了西区决赛，
the Jazz dominated the Western Conference playoffs.
而且还有十天的休息。
and would have ten days' rest.
而公牛队与溜马队还得在东部继续战斗。
while the Bulls and Pacers continued to battle in the East.
公牛队又输掉了一场比赛，
The Bulls lost another game,
于是多年来不得不第一次打满七场的系列赛。
and would have to go the full seven in a series for the first time in years.
第六场比赛快要结束时，还有人质疑说，
By the end of game six, doubters were saying.
麦可最终会扑个空。
that Michael was finally running on empty.
公牛队落后两分，
Bulls trail by two.
开始了，乔丹一对一迈基，
Here we go.MJ one-on-one with McKey.
麦可突破，绊到自己的脚摔倒了，
Michael a drive, tripped off his feet,
迈基抢到了球,溜马会赢。
and McKey stole the ball, and that's going to do it.
他们会赢。
That will do it.
印第安那会赢得比赛。
Indiana's going to win it.
那晚他可能被打垮了，
He may have been devastated that night,
我假设他被打垮了，但他有能力去相信
and I assume he was, but he had the ability to believe...
我们会赢，而且他也会做好。
that we were going to win. And he was going to do well.
可能最为神奇的一投，
Probably one of the most remarkable shots.
是大家都记得的乔丹对抗克里夫兰的那一球。
that everybody remembers is the shot he made against Cleveland.
发球传给了乔丹，
The in-bounds pass comes in to Jordan.
麦可罚球线附近,
Here's Michael at the foul line.
伊洛面前跳投，
A shot on Ehlo.
球进啦！
Good!
公牛赢了！
The Bulls win!
他们获胜了！
They win it!
但是大家不记得，
But they don't remember.
之前的晚上，若他不是六罚错失三罚的话
that the night before, he missed three out of six foul shots.
对我们来说就已经封杀比赛了，
that would have sealed the game for us,
而我们也不必打第五场了。
and we wouldn't have had to go to the fifth game.
一位普通的球员会说“哦，我浪费了这个机会，
A normal player would have said, "Oh, I cost us this opportunity，
差点就把对手打败。”
and probably beat themselves up over it."
而麦可第二天在去克利夫兰的巴士上说，
Michael, the next day that we played Cleveland got on the bus and said，
“不用害怕，我们会赢得比赛的。”
"Have no fear.We're going to win this ball game."
“如果我们就坐在这儿担心别人怎么想我们，
"If we sit here and worry about what people think of us,
那我们肯定没有机会。
then we don't have a chance.
他们还得过芝加哥这关。
They still got to come through Chicago.
犹他，印第安那,他们还得过芝加哥这关。
Utah, Indiana, they still got to come through Chicago.
我不在乎今天发生了什么，
I don't care what happens today,
也不在乎其它系列赛的情况，
don't care what happened in the other series.
他们都还是得过芝加哥。
They still got to come through Chicago.
我们会赢第七场。”
We will win game seven."
印第安那的球，麦可抄截，
Indiana the ball.Michael a steal.
乔丹运球快攻，他要扣篮了。
MJ on the run, he will dunk the ball.
麦可正面对着最终的淘汰，
Michael was facing the ultimate elimination.
输球，就会以失败划下职业生涯的句点。
lose, and end his career on a note of defeat.
且不管麦可的承诺，
Despite Michael's promises,
刚开始时溜马还领先了13分呢。
the Pacers led by 13 points early on.
于是麦可带领公牛队重整旗鼓。
Then Michael led the Bulls on a furious rally.
乔丹，防守松了，突破，扣篮，还犯规啦！
He's loose, driving, and dunks the ball, and a foul!
那就是带领公牛队
It was the kind of run that had led the Bulls
赢得前五次冠军的动力。
to their five previous championships.
不过比赛还有一半要打。
But there was still a half of basketball to play.
你来到的是东区决赛，第七场，
You were in the conference finals.In the seventh game,
我们是以落后的分数
we were down
进入第四节的。
going into the fourth quarter.
我以为也许...也许就是这样。
And I thought maybe...maybe this is it.
也许这就是我们最后的欢呼了。
maybe we've had the last hurrah.
但在我们英雄的带领下，球员士气开始高涨。
But something rose up in these players, led by our hero.
他是那种肯为你跳下桥
He's the type of man that could get you to jump off a bridge
或者至少会考虑几分钟的人。
or at least think about it for a few seconds.
他拥有一种要完成使命的意志力，
He has such a will to accomplish a mission.
每个人都追随他。
that everyone follows him.
麦可回到弧顶，
Michael back to the top.
现在换防回对迈基。
and now the switch made back by McKey.
麦可到禁区，跳起传给路克，
Michael to the lane, jumped out to Luc.
17尺...命中！
17-footer...bang!
进展顺利！
Down the well it goes.
乔丹带球前进，传给科尔投三分，
MJ on the run, to Kerr for three.
科尔！
Kerr!
乔丹...
MJ...
后仰跳投精彩！
Fall away jumper shot is good!
还犯规啦！
And a foul!
在比赛最后的几分钟他们的脚可能累了，
They may have had tired legs,
但是麦可和公牛队成长得更加强大。
but Michael and the Bulls grew stronger in the game's final minutes.
公牛队获胜，88比83。
Bulls win, 88-83.
公牛队再次挺进总决赛！
They go to the finals again.
麦可，你累死了吧，对吗？
Michael, you're a tired man, aren't you?
我简直是虚脱了，但那才能带领我们迈向我们的目标。
I'm exhausted. But that's what it took to get to where we had to go.
我是说，每个人得放手一搏，
I mean, everybody had to leave it on the floor.
没有第二次机会，那是最后一支舞了，
it's no tomorrow, it's the last dance,
所以我们必须全力以赴。
so we got to give everything we got.
犹他休息了，你们却筋疲力尽，
They're rested, you guys are fatigued,
但是我知道你们会在星期三准备好迎战的。
but I know you'll be ready to play on Wednesday.
我们的心志不累，
Our hearts are not fatigued.
那是最重要的事情。
That's the most important thing.
好的，麦可，精彩的比赛。
All right, Michael, great job.
在他最后的退出之前
Before making his final exit,
麦可还得再次出现在聚光灯下。
Michael had to take one more walk through the spotlight.
如果你和乔丹一起走在人群中，
If you walk through a crowd with Jordan,
你看到他所看到一样的东西，你看到所有目光聚集，
you see the same thing he sees. you see all the eyes aiming in.
于是我问，“你在人群之中看到了什么？”
And I asked, "What do you see in the crowd?"
而他说，“有时候，我见到一个父亲和一个孩子。”
And he said, "Sometimes,I'll see a father and a son.
“他们也许没有觉得我注意到他们，”
"They may not think I've even noticed them,
乔丹说，“但有时会有，”
but sometimes,"Jordan will say,
“我想他们不知我是多么想像他们一样。”
"I wonder if they have any idea how much I'd like to be them."
昨晚一开始的新闻，
Last night we began the show.
是乔丹父亲失踪的消息。
with the disappearance of Michael Jordan's father.
今晚，最严重的担心还是发生了。
Tonight, the worst fears have come true.
詹姆斯·乔丹被发现时已身亡...
James Jordan was found dead...
谋杀案的受害者。
the victim of an apparent murder.
当我父亲去世时，我已拥有他32年了。
When my father died,I had him for 32 years.
我很幸运，
I was very lucky,
我把它看成是件幸运的事儿，
I looked at it as being lucky,
并不因他已经不在了而沮丧，
not as being disappointed that he wasn't around anymore.
我觉得幸运的是当我需要他时他在。
I was lucky that he was there when I needed him.
他影响了我人生对一些情况的看法，
that he could influence my life to look at situations.
到今天我用以帮助自己做决定。
that I use to help make my decisions to this day.
有些小孩甚至从没父亲。
Some kids never have Dad.
当然，现在我也想拥有他，但是，
Sure, I would love to have him now, but.
人们来到这地球是有原因的，而且你在这享用人生，
people are put on this earth for a reason,and you utilize the time that you're here.
你永远不知何时那会被夺走。
You never know when that's going to be taken away from you.
那是他教会我的，
That's one thing he taught me.
而当你活着，或他人活着，
But while he's here, or while they're here,
就应当对某些人的人生产生影响，
they should make an impact on someone's life.
而他对我的人生产生了影响。
And he made an impact on my life.
你会得到的，伙计！
You're going to get it, man!
这是回报你把我带到世上的。
That's for bringing me into this world.
在第三个冠军后
After the third championship,
我父亲曾暗示我去打棒球，
my father kept kind of hinting towards me playing baseball.
“不要打篮球了，
"Stop playing basketball.
为何不尝试打棒球呢？”
Why don't you give your baseball a shot?"
因为那才是最初他真正教我玩的（运动）
Because that's what he actually got me started playing.
六岁大时我打棒球，
when I was six years old I played baseball.
而他也觉得我能打棒球，
And he felt that I could play baseball.
用打篮球相同的信念和态度
and do it with the same conviction and attitude.
去打棒球。
that I played basketball.
每天，在太阳升起之前的第一个人会是乔丹，
Everyday, the first person there before the sun would be Jordan.
而他这么早在那儿因为是他不够好。
And he was there because he wasn't good.
他会和打击教练一起，
He would work with a batting instructor.
训练一整天，
and work all day long.
而他也是每晚最后离开的人。
and be the last person to leave every night also.
三振出局！
Strike three!
那小子真烂
Money's no Stan Musial.
但他在尝试呀。
But he's trying.
说，嘿，他又不是威利梅斯（电影大联盟中的球员之一）
Say, hey, he's no Willie Mays.
但是他有努力呀，伙计。
But he's trying, man.
打棒球让我学到的是：别害怕去尝试。
What it did teach me was, don't be afraid to try.
能发生的最严重的事儿
The worst thing that can happen
就是你想像的道路走不通罢了，
is it doesn't... it doesn't pan out the way that you envision it.
但是至少你要试试看。
But at least you know that by giving it a shot.
人们都说，
People were basically saying.
我不应出现在这项运动，
that I didn't have no reason being in the sport,
还有我使这项运动变低级了。
and I was degrading the sport.
当这些负面的东西开始发生时，
When those negative things started to happen,
唯一的事情是，我希望我父亲在，
the only thing，I wish my father was there.
给我一些我积极的帮助。
to give me the positive reinforcements that I needed.
我问他早晨感觉怎样。
I asked him what it was like for him in the morning.
他说，我在太阳升起前起来，
And Jordan said, I get up before the sun comes up,
我帮自己弄了点早餐，
and I make myself some breakfast by myself.
他一个人去到那，
he was down there alone.
我上到车，
and I get in the car.
开车去春训，
And I'm driving to spring training,
路上还没有半个人。
and there's no one, really, out on the roads yet.
而我看看旁边的座位看见我父亲，
And I look at the seat next to me and I see my Dad,
我跟他说，
and I talk to him.
“我自己在想，老爸！我们要一起练习”
"I think to myself, Pop, we're doing this.
We're doing this together."
一天快结束了，
And the day would end,
而他会和打击教练说，
and he would say to the batting instructor,
“我们可以再多练一会吗？
"Can we do a little more?
我觉得我开始上手了，
I think I'm getting this.
我觉得我有学到，我觉得我开始上手了”
I think I'm learning this, I think I'm getting this."
而就那时运动画刊则以他做为封面，
And that's when Sports Illustrated put him on the cover.
写着“乔丹羞辱了棒球！”
saying that Michael Jordan has embarrassed baseball!
而每晚我会看他，
And as I would watch him there every night.
太阳快要下山时，其他球员都离开后，
as the sun was going down and the other ball players had left,
我看到这伙计做得更好了，
and I would see this guy working to get better.
麦可.乔丹做得更好了。
Michael Jordan working to get better.
我不禁会想到如果你也有孩子，
I couldn't help thinking that if you ever have children,
你应该祈祷某天他们长大，
you ought to pray that they grow up someday.
会让你这样难堪。
to embarrass you like this.
麦可·乔丹...
Michael Jordan...
击出了飞球。
hits a fly ball.
我想经验的本身有种动力
I think that experience itself kind of gave him a blessing
使他重回篮坛，
of coming back to basketball.
还有他对他在比赛场上的天赋的理解
and understanding the gift that he'd been given for this game.
是那么的特别。
that was so special.
当麦可回来，
When Michael came back,
我和雅德开车去比赛，
and Jud and I were driving down to the game,
我问，“雅德，你知道，菲尔让麦可首发吗？”
and I said, "Jud, you know, does Phil start Michael?
“我意思是，他已经离开赛场，你知道，60，65场了。”
I mean, he hasn't been here for, you know, 60 games, 65 games."
而雅德看着我说，
And Jud looked at me and he said,
“史蒂夫，一般来说，
"Steve, as a general rule,
当你在球场外有自己的塑像的话，
when you have your own statue outside the stadium,
你就不用坐板凳了。”
you don't come off the bench."
毫无疑问，还有其他伟大的球员，
There'll be other great players, there's no question about that.
但是他对比赛所做的一切，
But what he's done for the game.
我不认为有人能到像他这么伟大。
I don't think anybody will touch his greatness.
那就是为何大家比赛结束后还是在那，
and that's why everybody's holding on here in the finish.
参与其中，如果这真是他的最后一赛季，
to just be apart of，if this is the last run,
每一人都愿参与其中见证那一刻。
everybody wants to be apart of it and witness it.
公牛队曾五次打入总决赛，
The Bulls had gone to the finals five times,
而且五次他们都赢了。
and five times they had won.
事实上这可能是麦可最后的机会，
The fact that this might be Michael's last chance.
使得这次决赛最具期待性。
made these finals the most anticipated ever.
爵士队依靠常规赛的战绩获得主场优势，
The Jazz had earned the home court advantage on the strength of their regular season.
而今，世界目光都聚集
And now, the world tuned in
见证麦可能否突破逆境，
to see if Michael could beat the odds.
最后再赢一次。
and win one last time.
麦可转身，跳起，出手，得分！
Michael circles, spins, hangs, fires, scores!
在第一场，公牛把爵士带入了加时赛，
In game one, the Bulls took the Jazz into overtime.
但最后，精力充沛的爵士队获胜了。
But in the end, fresher legs prevailed.
虽然去年犹他输了
The previous year, although Utah had lost,
但他们向自己证明，
they had proven to themselves.
他们能与公牛队抗衡，
that they could play with the Bulls.
而且他们赢了第一场，
and then they win game one.
我以为犹他会成为总冠军呢。
I thought Utah was going to be the NBA champions.
当人们，在某些方面，不期待你赢，
When everybody, in some ways, didn't expect me to win,
你成功的机会很渺茫，
and the odds are stacked against you.
在生命中你曾经是个失败者，
And for once in your life, you are the underdog.
你知道，对我来说那是很美好的。
You know, that was beautiful for me.
当他最需要它时，在他竖起冠军旗帜的过程中，
When he needed it most, Michael didn't find comfort
麦可发现并没有那么容易，
in the championship banners he helped raise.
而是比之前七年的胜利需要更多的耐力
But rather strength from the seven years of defeat that came before.
那是一条漫长的道路。
That was a long road.
它使我整个夏天待在体育馆，锻炼自己的技术，
It kept me in the gym in the summer, working on my skills.
努力尝试成为我能成为的最好的球员。
trying to be the best basketball player I could become.
但在同时，为了给有着相同精神韧性
But at the same time,to show players who were not on the same level.
却不同能力的球员示范，
with the same mental toughness.
如果我要去做，
that, if I'm going to do this,
你就不得不得跟上节奏。
then you have to keep up with the pace.
静静地，它就开始转变，
And quietly, it started to turn.
他是你最努力的工作者，他每天都在比拼。
He was your hardest worker. He competed everyday.
带动你的整个球队进步，像一位教练一样。
That filtered down through your team, so as a coach.
你从不需谈论你球队的职业道德，
you never had to talk about the work ethic of your team.
因为你最好的球员总会做榜样。
because your best player always brought that.
对于许多他的旧队友来说
Michael's standards were too high...
麦可的标准很高，
for many of his early teammates.
不过之后史考蒂.皮朋来了，
but then came Scottie Pippen.
麦可对史考蒂.皮朋的影响几乎从第一天就开始了。
The influence of Michael on Scottie Pippen was almost from day one.
麦可常在球场上协助他，
Michael kind of helped him get out there on the basketball court.
教他一些小事情，一些他用的小技巧，
and taught him some little things. some of the small tricks that he'd use.
结果，他们俩配合得真的很好。
As a consequence, the two of them really played well together.
毋庸置疑，就像游侠传奇一样，
It was the Lone Ranger and Tonto.There's no doubt about it.
皮朋凭借自己的努力成为了一位明星，
Pippen became a star in his own right.
于是我们有了精兵强将。
and then there was the supporting cast.
麦可不屈不挠地挑战，知道当他们俩的时刻来临时要准备好。
that Michael would challenge relentlessly, knowing that they two had to be ready when their moment came.
他知道每个人在比赛中必须得分担，
He understood the fact that everybody had to share in the game,
而他也愿意成为这其中的一部份，
and that he was willing to be part of this.
为此他会牺牲一些属于自己的比赛，
to sacrifice some of his own game for that.
那是非常重要的事情。
was the most important thing.
他走开后，我会准备好。
He comes off, I'll be ready.
我获得了较多的上场机会，
I've gotten a chance to play a lot,
在重要的比赛中打很长时间
and play a lot in big games.
而我也感觉到了压力，我觉得，
And I felt the pressure, I think,
我可能表现得不那么好
and didn't perform that well.
我学着如何与麦可打比赛和投入关键球，
And I learned how to play with Michael and how to hit big shots,
如何在那种局面放松自己。
and how to relax myself in situations like that.
麦可，陷入包夹，传给科尔。
Michael, in traffic, to Kerr.
15尺...进了！
15-footer... Yeah!
多么美好的经验啊，你知道，能经历，
What a great experience, you know, to go through,
不仅仅是为了篮球，还有是为了以后的人生，
not just for basketball, but for the rest of my life.
知道自己能够面对那些挺难的，
To know that I can face something.
些事情，而且能应对它。
that's pretty difficult, and deal with it.
回到犹他，
Back in Utah.
爵士队还是如首胜时一样顽强，
the buzz was still about the Jazz's series opening victory.
但在第二场比赛开始后，
But by the time game two had begun,
第一场已成为麦可和公牛队的过去了。
game one was history to Michael and the Bulls.
如果麦可乐于当弱者，
If Michael enjoyed being the underdog,
他就不会让他队友感到它们是一个团队，带着美好的理想
he never let his team feel like one, driving them forward
和冠军的自信鞭策他们前进。
with the fair and confidence of a champion.
公牛队赢得了第二场比赛，
The Bulls won game two,
而现在比赛将移师芝加哥，1:1。
and now the series would move to Chicago, tied at one.
我很乐于见到有人能打败乔丹四次,
I'd have to see someone beat Michael Jordan four times,
因为，我说过，要那样做你得肢解他，
because, I said, to do that you're going to have to dismember him.
你得要砍下他的一只手和一只脚，
You're going to have to take an arm and leg,
如果你要把他拖到地板上，
and you're going to have to drag him off the floor.
他也不会轻易服从。
He's not going to go easily.
这可能会是麦可在芝加哥最后的几场比赛了，
These would be Michael's last games in Chicago.
而第三场比赛打起来就像是感谢球迷的表演赛。
And game three played out like a thank-you note to the fans.
芝加哥以96-54赢得第三场比赛
Chicago's 96-54 win in game three was the biggest rout.
是在NBA总决赛历史上最大的比分差距。
in NBA finals history.
公牛队离冠军还剩两场胜利。
The Bulls were two games away from the title.
人们都说我们的身体疲惫。
People say a lot of things about our physical tiredness,
但是我们的精神强韧。
but our mental toughness is there.
我认为那是不容忽视的。
And I don't think that should ever be over looked.
好的，开始了。
Okay, here we go.
好的，加油！
Okay, let's go!
在统治了第三场比赛后，
After dominating game three,
公牛队的身体韧性在第四场比赛受到考验。
the Bulls' physical resilience would be tested in game four
史考蒂找人。
Scottie looks.
传给了麦可...MJ
Dumps it to Michael...MJ
转身走底线，
And turns base line.
后仰跳投...得分！
Fall away jumper...good!
多么完美的弧线！
What a rainbow that was.
库科奇传给麦可，
Kukoc drops to Michael.
乔丹底线转身，跳起得分
MJ spins along the base line, goes up and scores.
库科奇在找人，在找人，在找人。
And Kukoc looking, looking, looking.
看到了麦可，他接球，运了两下，转身，勾射，
Look to Michael. He catches, two dribbles, spins in, scoops.
进了！
and scores!
公牛又赢得一场胜利，
Another win for the Bulls.
冠军之路仅一场胜利之遥了。
The countdown to the championship had reached one.
三胜一负，
Three-one.
你觉得你们是居于劣势吗？
Do you still feel like you guys are the underdogs?
不，我们现在掌控大局。
No, we're in the driver's seat right now.
还有，你知道，我们得出来，
and, you know, we just have to come out.
准备打下一场比赛，
ready to play next game,
然后，你知道，把冠军奖杯拿回来。
and, you know, try to put it away.
在第五场比赛之前，庆祝就已经开始了。
Before game five, the celebration had already begun.
我可以问你吗，这在IMAX的萤幕上看起来有多大？
Can I ask you, how big does that look on IMAX?
像是在IMAX的萤幕上巨桶爆米花吗？
Does look like a gigantic bucket of popcorn on an IMAX screen?
它像是整座山一样,伙计。
It's a whole mountain of it, folks.
好了，各位。
All right, baby.
加油，伙计。
Come on, man.
全力以赴。
all for the heart.
在篮球场上全力表现。
and lay it out on the basketball court.
当我们从球场走出来时，
When we come out of the court,
我们都在庆祝了，而乔也将会高兴的。
we're all celebrating, and joe's going to be happy.
让我们上场吧，各位！
Let's go, baby.
在真正的庆祝之前，
Before there was anything to really celebrate,
卡尔·马龙与爵士队找到了
Karl Malone and the Jazz found an answer
对付公牛队做的每一动作的答案。
to every move the Bulls made.
第五场，公牛队输了。
In game five, the Bulls came up empty,
而麦可最后一次走出联合中心。
and Michael walked out of the United Center for the last time.
第二天回到犹他练习时，
Back in Utah for practice the following day,
输球的事儿已被抛诸脑后，
the defeat was already forgotten,
因为自从麦可的第一次冠军
for here was another secret to the spell Michael had held...
他还拥有另一个联盟其他球队
over the rest of the league.
所没有的秘诀。
ever since his first championship.
即使当公牛队的身体状况不是很好，
Even when the Bulls weren't superior physically,
他们还有心灵上的哲理优势。
they had a philosophical edge.
我想菲尔对于“禅”做了很多的研究，
I think Phil had a lot to do with that with his Zen practice.
他将所有的情感方式都注入球赛中。
His whole emotional approach to a game of basketball
我曾跟过许多不同的教练，
I've experienced a lot of different coaches,
但是他从一个完全不同框架，
but he gave me the understanding about life...
让我了解人生的意义。
in a whole different frame.
我认为他对禅学的理解是
I think his teaching toward the understanding of Zen Buddhism is
教导你如何认知你自己。
how you view yourself.
去应对你生活环境中的现实情况，
to deal with the realities of life surrounding you,
不知怎么的能把一场简单的篮球赛
and somehow be able to correlate that.
联系起来。
to a simple game as basketball.
这是我们讨论过很多次的
This is something that we talked about a lot
作为一支球队
as a basketball team,
如何在那些可能发生的任何事情的时刻做出应对。
is about how to be in the moment being able to visualize what might happen in those times.
麦可深信这些，
Michael so embraced this,
而我也觉得那是他比赛的魅力，
and I think that was the beauty of his game,
就是他有那些能力去调整，
is that he had all these abilities to adjust,
不会硬是实行他预定的想法。
not force his own predetermined idea,
当那些事情在他的比赛中发生。
but allow those things to come together for his game.
我倾向冷静，事情发展变得缓慢，
I tend to be calm, things tend to slowdown.
当我碰到一个大家无法预测的情况时，
As I go into situations that people don't know the outcome,
我已经在心里体验一遍了，
I've already experienced them in my mind.
和自己玩一次先。
just playing tricks with myself.
所以它对我而言并不新鲜而我也不怕没能战胜它。
So it didn't seem new to me and I wasn't afraid to fail with it.
一旦我开始理解那些，
Once I began to understand that,
我便成为一位篮球大师了。
I became a master of the game of basketball.
在犹他的第六场，
Game six in Utah.
对公牛队来说，一场胜利就意味着冠军。
for the Bulls, a win would mean the championship.
对麦可而言，那会是他传奇的继续巩固。
For Michael, it would mean the cementing of his legacy.
哈柏在看左边，不是那儿...吊高球，
Harper looking left, not there...backdoor lob.
麦可跳起上篮得分！
Michael goes up and scores!
由于史考蒂.皮朋的背伤，
The Bulls were still feeling the effects of game five.
公牛队仍受到第五场的影响。
as a bad back grounded Scottie Pippen.
皮朋摔倒了但他努力站了起来，
Pippen knocked down and he's struggling to get back up.
作挡拆，麦可跳起，投蓝，得分！
Sets a screen. Michael hangs in the air. His jumper, good!
在芝加哥，球迷挤满了麦可·乔丹的餐厅，
In Chicago, fans filled Michael Jordan's restaurant,
而联合中心也涌进了23000名忠实的球迷。
and 23,000 of the faithful filled the United Center.
回到犹他，麦可执行着自己的想法，
Back in Utah, Michael was operating on his own.
爵士队著名的团队合作频频奏效，
the celebrated teamwork of the Jazz was clicking,
卡尔.马龙和约翰.斯托克顿掌控了比赛。
and Karl Malone and John Stockton took charge of the game.
在一个疲惫不堪的季后赛后，
After a grueling post-season,
公牛队已经跟不上爵士队了。
the Bulls could no longer match up with the Jazz man for man.
带着第四节的领先，爵士人们感觉到
With a fourth-quarter lead, the Utah crowd sensed
胜利随着每一球都拉得越来越近了。
victory drawing closer with every basket.
对于公牛队，最后一位战士依然屹立不倒努力拉回比赛。
For the Bulls，the last man standing clawed his way back into the game.
加油！公牛队！
Come on, Bulls!
进攻时间还有7秒，6秒，5秒。
Seven on the shot box, six, five.
麦可决定自己来。
Now Michael's got to do it himself.
乔丹假动作，假动作，跳起，
Jordan backing, backing, pumping,
后仰，投篮，命中！
falling, firing, scores!
还犯规了，哦，天哪！
And a foul! Ohh, my!
哈柏回传外线，
Harper backing outside.
麦可出手，再度命中三分！
Michael firing, sticks another three!
他几乎打满了比赛的每一分钟，
He had played nearly every minute of the game,
而得分超过他队友的一半。
and scored more than half of his team's points.
但是在第四节的后期，
But late in the fourth quarter,
麦可最后似乎努力得不行了，
Michael finally seemed worn out by his efforts.
他的命中率开始下滑。
and his shots faltered.
霍纳塞克带球，
Hornacek running.
霍纳塞克投三分，命中！
Hornacek for three.Got it!
但麦可仍未放弃，不断投篮，
Still Michael kept coming, kept shooting,
继续站到罚球线上，使公牛队紧咬差距。
kept getting to the line, kept the Bulls in the game.
你能做到的！四连冠！
You can do it! Four championships in a row!
一切就像是他一直以来所做的
It was as if everything he had ever accomplished.
而带领他进入了这种时刻。
had led Michael to this one moment.
在比赛最后的一分钟，
And in the final minute of the game,
乔丹职业生涯的最后一分钟，
at the final minute of his career,
他需要拿出他一路上所学一切。
he would need everything he had learned along the way.
皮朋在找人，快到发球时限时传给了麦可。
Pippen looking，dump to Michael near the time line.
MJ对罗素。
MJ at Russell.
麦可一个突破，上篮得分！
Michael a drive, and the lay-up is good.
麦可的一个突破上篮
A driving lay-up by Michael.
使公牛队落后1分，86-85
draws the Bulls to within one, 86-85.
现在你有机会在这结束它了。
And now you got a chance for a stop here.
丹尼斯和卡尔去到低位，
Dennis and Karl are going to get down on the post,
他们会做些必要的身体冲撞。
and they're going to do all their little necessary banging.
我自己，注意力在卡尔身上，
Myself, I focused on Karl.
霍纳塞克单挡过去。
Hornacek screens across.
马龙去到低位，
Malone to the post.
当他正与丹尼斯对抗时，
While he's fighting with Dennis,
他忘记了球的位置，
he basically forgets where the ball is,
所以我选择这次机会去做个抄截，
and so I choose this opportune time to make my steal,
然后我就回头把球拍掉了。
and I came back to strip the ball away.
马龙被麦可拍掉球！摔倒在了地板上，乔丹抄截！
Malone stripped by Michael!To the floor, stolen by MJ!
麦可一个抄截！还剩16秒，公牛队落后1分。
Michael a steal! Sixteen seconds left. Bulls down one.
观众变得安静。
Crowd gets quiet.
那一刻开始变成了特定的时刻，你知道，属于我的，
The moment starts to become the moment, you know, for me.
一旦你遇到了这种时刻，你知道你在。
Once you get in the moment, you know you're there.
当我看到那时刻，
And when I saw the moment.
是机会利用它时，我从未怀疑过自己，
the opportunity to take advantage of it. I never doubted myself.
知道这是会是最后的机会，
Knowing that this was going to be the last opportunity.
非赢即输。
to either win the game or lose it.
麦可对抗罗素，
Michael against Russell.
11秒，10秒...乔丹.
Eleven, ten...Jordan.
乔丹突破，跳起，出手...
Jordan a drive, hangs, fires...
得分！
Scores!
公牛队赢得冠军！
Bulls win the title!
公牛队再度成为世界冠军！
The Bulls are the world champs again!
如果那是麦可·乔丹的最后的画面
If that's the last image of Michael Jordan,
多么的伟大啊！
how magnificent is it!
哦，天啊！那太漂亮啦！
Oh, my God! that was beautiful.
不可思议的终结！
What a finish!
我心存信念！我心存信念！
I had faith! I had faith!
你肯定有。
You bet you did.
他的第六次MVP
His sixth MVP
本赛季，他在NBA总决赛
this past season,and his sixth MVP
的第六次MVP。麦可·乔丹！
in the NBA finals. Michael Jordan!
麦可·乔丹的传奇是真实的。
Michael Jordan's legacy is authenticity.
如果你移去所有的大肆宣传
If you removed all the hype,
市场作用，炫目的表演，
all the marketing, all the show-time glitz,
他也像任何一个在体育馆或是任何时间地点打球的人一样的百分之百真实。
he would be as 100% genuine as anybody who ever played in a gym or an armory anywhere anytime.
再不会有一位球员
There's never been a player
拥有麦可·乔丹拥有的那些能力，
that's had that ability that Michael Jordan's had...
像他在篮球场上那样战斗。
in the kind of way he did it in this game of basketball.
他的传奇像是个新生儿而十年之后，
His legacy is a newborn child ten years from now.
会有个父亲说“真希望你有看过乔丹。”
and a father says, "I wish you could have seen Michael Jordan."
感谢你
Thank you.
在球场上的优雅与尊严。
The dignity and grace with which you conduct yourself off the court
那些是很重要的事，我相信那是历久不衰的经典。
those are important things,and I believe those are enduring things.
你如果计算，我不知道，或许两万五千年，
You figure there've been, I don't know, 25,000 years.
我不知道你怎样计算，
I don't know how you do the math of that,
但是你想挑选五万名最好的运动员，
but that's like out of all 50,000 top athletes.
从你知道的，包括史前的雷龙和翼龙，
since, you know, prehistoric times brontosaurus and pterodactyls included.
他都会在其中的！
he's right there!
十年之后，二十年之后，
Ten years from now, 20 years from now...
我听到人们在说的
I hear people saying,
或是希望人们去说的，很简单，
or l would want people to say, and it's simple...
如果麦可.乔丹还在打球赛的话，
that if Michael Jordan was still playing the game of basketball,
他会统治比赛。
he would dominate.
不管篮球事业发生了什么事情，
No matter what happens in this business of basketball,
即使我们不拿一分钱，
if we didn't get paid a dime,
你还会去某个地方打球。
you still would play the game of basketball somewhere.
在某个地方会有个小孩在努力，
Somewhere there's a kid working.
他不省略任何步骤，
He won't skip any steps.
他会以我为榜样来学习，
He will learn from my example,
就像我也以他人学习一样。
just as I have learned from others.
将来会有位比我伟大的球员的。
There will be a player greater than me.